Finding Aid for William G. Dow Papers, 1927-1999
Bentley Historical Library
William G. Dow Papers
1927-1999
1930-1960
Bentley Historical Library
Dow, William G. (William Gould), 1895-
87210 Aa 2
16 linear feet
Professor of electrical engineering at the University of Michigan. Files documenting his scientific research and professional activities, notably his studies of high-frequency power welding, vacuum tube development, gas discharge plasma, microwave electron tubes, use of rockets and satellites in investigations of the upper atmosphere, missile guidance systems, and military electronics; files relating to his involvement with various University of Michigan research centers and institutes; and photographs.
The collection (Donor No. 7412 ) came to the library beginning in January 1987. A second accession was received in April 2000 following Professor Dow's death.
The collection is open for research.
William Gould Dow was a member of the faculty of the University of Michigan Department of Electrical Engineering from 1926 to 1964. He served as chairman of the department from 1958 until 1964. While at the University of Michigan, Dow was instrumental in establishing the University's Willow Run Research Laboratories and initiated several research programs in the Electrical Engineering Department, including the Plasma Engineering Laboratory and the Space Physics Research Laboratory. He helped found the Environmental Research Institute of Michigan (ERIM), and served on its board of directors until 1990. He was extremely active as a member of several professional societies, including the American Institute of Electrical Engineers (AIEE) and the Institute of Electrical & Electronic Engineers (IEEE). In addition to his teaching and administrative activities, Dow conducted significant basic and applied research in the areas of high-frequency power welding, vacuum tube development, gas discharge plasma, microwave electron tubes, use of rockets and satellites in investigations of the upper atmosphere, missile guidance systems, and military electronics.
Dow was born September 30, 1895 in Faribault, Minnesota. He received a BS degree from the University of Minnesota in 1916 and an electrical engineering degree in 1917. Between 1917 and 1926 Dow was employed with Westinghouse Electric Company, working in sales and product testing. Dow joined the University of Michigan's Electrical Engineering Department in 1926 as an instructor in electronics. He received his M.S.E. in 1929, and was made an assistant professor. Dow was promoted to associate professor in 1938 and to full professor in 1945. He served as chairman of the department from 1958 until 1964. In 1965 Dow retired, continuing to hold an appointment as professor emeritus until 1997.
From 1943 to 1945, Dow was on leave at the Radio Research Laboratory, Harvard University, conducting war-related research for the federal Office of Scientific Research and Development. He directed research in high-frequency radio transmission as a radar countermeasure. In that capacity, Dow spent three months in 1944-1945 in Britain, overseeing installation of radar jamming equipment and surveying British vacuum tube research laboratories for the Vacuum Tube Development Committee of the National Defense Research Committee (NDRC), of which he was a member.
During and after the war, Dow was involved in many industry and government-sponsored projects. Among the major projects were an investigation of a sheet metal welding technique for the Fisher Body Division of General Motors; consulting for the National Bureau of Standards (1945-1955) on problems relating to vacuum tubes; a variety of projects for the Signal Corps, Air Force, and Army Ordnance relating to microwave electron tubes, particularly magnetrons; and a number of investigations of management and personnel issues at military installations and research laboratories.
Dow served on the prestigious Rocket and Satellite Research Panel from 1946 until 1960; this group coordinated all military-supported programs toward determining the properties of the upper atmosphere. He was also a member of the Technical Panel on Rocketry of the International Geophysical Year (1956-1959). He was a member of the American Institute of Electrical Engineers (AIEE), the Institute of Electrical and Electronic Engineers (IEEE), the Institute of Radio Engineers (IRE), and other professional organizations. In addition to numerous technical articles, Dow published Fundamentals of Electrical Engineering, for many years a standard textbook in the field.
Dow held an appointment as Senior Research Geophysicist at the Space Physics Research Lab from 1966-1971. He was a charter member of the Board of Directors of the Environmental Research Institute of Michigan, serving on the board from 1972 until 1990, and as a trustee emeritus until 1997. Later in life he worked on efforts to produce thermonuclear fusion, for which he received two patents in the 1980s. Dow continued to live in Ann Arbor until 1997, when he moved to Waco, Texas and Bellevue, Washington.
The William G. Dow Papers document his career as a faculty member of the University of Michigan Department of Electrical Engineering, his scientific research, his participation in professional organizations, and his other professional interests and activities. The collection also contains copies of published and unpublished technical and professional papers written by Dow, and two unpublished books. The papers include lecture notes taken by Dow, texts of lectures given by Dow and others, course materials used in Dow's classes, correspondence, minutes, reports, raw data, photographs, and other material relating to Dow's research. The papers are composed of six series: University of Michigan Activities, Research, Professional Organizations, Articles, Books and Talks, Topical Files, Correspondence, and Photographs. There is a great deal of overlap between theses series, as Dow was often engaged in educational, research, publishing, and professional activities simultaneously. Researchers are advised to consult the entire collection. A small group of biographical and bibliographical materials begins the collection.
Astronautics -- History.; Electric engineering.; Electron tubes.; Electronics in rocketry.; Engineering -- Research.; Engineering -- Study and teaching -- United States.; Engineers -- Education -- United States.; Engineers -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Guided missiles -- Guidance systems.; Military engineering.; Military research -- United States.; Research, Industrial -- United States.; Rockets (Aeronautics) -- Research -- United States.; Rocketry -- Research -- United States.; Rocketry -- United States -- History.; V-2 rocket -- Scientific applications.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Science.; Rockets.; Photographs.; American Institute of Electrical Engineers.; Dow, William G. (William Gould), 1895-1999.; Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Electrical Engineering.; University of Michigan. Electronics Institute.; University of Michigan. Engineering Research Institute.; University of Michigan -- Faculty.; University of Michigan. Plasma Engineering Laboratory.; University of Michigan -- Research.; University of Michigan. Space Physics Research Laboratory.; University of Michigan. Willow Run Laboratories.; Dow, William G. (William Gould), 1895-1999.; University of Michigan. Electronics Institute.; University of Michigan -- Faculty.
- Biographical Information, 1945-1986
  - Biographical summaries, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1945-1960 (Box 1)
  - Reminiscences about early days, 1971-1986 (Box 1)
  - Bibliography (Box 1)
- University of Michigan Activities, 1927-1968
  In the University of Michigan Activities series, the largest subseries (Lecture Notes and Course Materials) contains materials relating to Dow's experiences both as a teacher and a student of electrical engineering. Materials in this subseries are divided into two sub-subseries: materials created by Dow and those relating to courses taught by others. Courses Dow taught are organized by course number, and these folders contain his notes, exercises, tests, and exams given to students. In many cases there seems to be an overlap between Dow's work as a teacher and his activities conducting industrial and government research, as demonstrated by the many pieces of correspondence with corporations which Dow indicated should be included in these files. Of particular interest may be the materials relating to the basic course in electronics developed by Dow which was required of all undergraduate students in electrical engineering at Michigan since 1929. According to The University of Michigan: An Encyclopedic Survey: "the College of Engineering of the University of Michigan was one of the first engineering schools in the United States to include instruction in electronics as a major item in its curriculum." (III, 1230) The extensive documentation of the courses Dow taught, together with his correspondence about education and the curriculum, may be of interest to those studying the evolution of this innovative program. Courses taught by people other than Dow are organized alphabetically by the professor's last name; these folders contain lecture notes rather than course materials.
  This series also includes the University of Michigan Research Centers subseries which contains materials relating to the founding and administration of the Aeronautical Research Center and the Engineering Research Center. Another subseries relates to the Summer Electronics Institute, of which Dow was the director. The files of the Institute include correspondence relating to the planning of the institute, programs, notes on lectures taken by him, and texts of several lectures by Institute instructors. In 1937 the topic of the Summer Institute was high vacuum electron tubes and gaseous conduction principles; in 1950 the topics were microwave electron tubes and semi-conductor electronics, and in 1955 it focused on transistor applications. Materials relating to other activities sponsored by or held at the University of Michigan are included in the Events at the University of Michigan subseries.
  - Lecture Notes and Course Materials, 1927-1964
    - Course Materials Created by Dow, 1927-1964
      - Correspondence about Education and Curriculum, 1927-1948 (Box 1)
      - EE3, 1954-1955 (Box 1)
      - EE12, 1931-1935 (Box 1)
      - EE81, Lab Data, Summer 1958 (Box 1)
      - EE100, 1954 (Box 1)
      - EE160, 1956-1957 (Box 1)
      - EE180, Reference, 1955-1960 (Box 1)
      - EE180, Student Work, 1932-1950 (Box 1)
      - EE180, Student Work, 1950-1955 (Box 1)
      - EE180, Student Work, 1956-1959 (Box 1)
      - EE181, Tracer Points, 1939-1946 (Box 1)
      - EE181, Theater Dimmer, 1940 (Box 1)
      - EE181, Welding, 1941-1942 (Box 1)
      - EE187, 1956-1960 (Box 1)
      - EE189, 1938-1956 (Box 1)
      - EE189, Resource File, 1928-1939 (Box 1)
      - EE189, Resource File, 1950-1959 (Box 1)
      - EE189, Resource File, 1960-1961 (Box 1)
      - EE189-283, 1934-1961 (Box 1)
      - EE283, Resource File, 1938-1959 (Box 1)
      - EE283, Resource File, 1960-1961 (Box 1)
      - EE285, Resource File, 1941-1948 (Box 1)
      - EE286, 1937-1949 (Box 1)
      - EE286, 1950-1958 (Box 1)
      - EE286, 1959-1962 (Box 2)
      - EE380, Resource File, 1946-1963 (Box 2)
      - EE380, Student Work, 1962-1964 (Box 2)
      - EE420 (Flint), 1963 (Box 2)
    - Notes for Courses Taught by Others, 1927-1943
      - S.S. Atwood, Insulation Properties, 1931 (Box 2)
      - W.L, Ayres, Math. 201-202, 1939-1940 (Box 2)
      - W.F. Colby, Physics 205, 1927 (Box 2)
      - W.F. Colby, Thermodynamics, 1937 (Box 2)
      - D.M. Dennison, Theoretical Mechanics, 1931-1932 (Box 2)
      - Otto LaPorte, Quantum Mechanics, 1937 (Box 2)
      - A.D. Moore, EE160 Materials, 1942-1943 (Box 2)
      - G.E. Uhlenbeck, Physics 207, Introduction to Theoretical Physics, 1928 (Box 2)
      - G.E. Uhlenbeck, Physics 216, Statistical Mechanics, 1928 (Box 2)
      - Seminar Notes, 1932-1933 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan Research Centers, 1946-1950
    - Aeronautical Research Center, 1948-1950
      - Operating Committee, 1948-1950 (Box 2)
      - Technical Steering Committee, 1949-1950 (Box 2)
    - Engineering Research Institute, 1946-1950
      - Minutes, 1949-1950 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1946-1949 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence, 1950 (Box 2)
  - Summer Electronics Institute, 1936-1955
    - 1937 Institute: High vacuum electron tubes and gaseous conduction principles, 1936-1937
      - Correspondence, July 1936-November 1937
        - July-December 1936 (Box 2)
        - March-April, 1937 (Box 2)
        - May-June, 1937 (Box 2)
        - July-November 1937 (Box 2)
      - Lecture Notes, Dushman, 1937 (Box 2)
      - Lecture Notes, F.B. Llewellyn, 1937 (Box 2)
      - Lecture Notes, L.B. Loeb, 1937 (Box 3)
      - Lecture Notes, H.E. Mendenhall, 1937 (Box 3)
      - Lecture Notes, B.J. Thompson and O'Neill, 1937 (Box 3)
      - Lecture Notes, U.K. Zworykin, 1937 (Box 3)
      - Photographs, 1937 (Box 3)
    - 1941 Institute
      - Correspondence, April-December 1941 (Box 3)
    - 1950 Institute: Microwave electron tubes and semi-conductor electronics, 1946-1950
      - Correspondence, April 1946-December 1950
        - April 1946-December 1949 (Box 3)
        - January-May 1950 (Box 3)
        - June-December 1950 (Box 3)
      - Program, 1950 (Box 3)
      - Lecture Notes, Apker-Findley, 1950 (Box 3)
        - Becker and Shive, 1950 (Box 3)
        - J.S. Donal, 1950 (Box 3)
        - Ginton-MacArthur, 1950 (Box 3)
        - McNall-Rittner (Box 3)
        - E.S. Ritter, 1950 (Box 3)
        - Shephard-Slater, 1950 (Box 3)
      - Photographs, 1950 (Box 3)
    - 1955 Institute: Transistor applications
      - Correspondence, January-March 1955 (Box 3)
      - Correspondence, April-October 1955 (Box 3)
      - Program, 1955 (Box 3)
      - Course Notes, EE401, 1955 (Box 3)
      - Course Notes, EE402, 1955 (Box 3)
      - Lecture Notes, 1955 (Box 3)
  - Events at the University of Michigan, 1950-1968
    - Aeronautical Engineering 50th Anniversary Convocation, 1964 (Box 4)
    - Air Force Institute of Technology (AFIT) Visit, 1964 (Box 4)
    - UM Chapter, The American Rocket Society, 1960-1962 (Box 4)
    - Automotive Lab Dedication, 1956 (Box 4)
    - Conference on Production Research Abroad, 1963 (Box 4)
    - Conference on Speech Recognition, 1963 (Box 4)
    - Conference on the University, 1962 (Box 4)
    - Course in Electronic Warfare, 1965-1966 (Box 4)
    - Electrical Engineering Research Review, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Electrical Engineering Research Review, Dow Speech, 1967; audio reel (Box 4)
    - Electron and Laser Beam Technology Symposium, 1966 (Box 4)
    - Electronics Showcase, 1964 (Box 4)
    - Engineering Convocation, 1966 (Box 4)
    - Engineering Sesquicentennial, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Engineering Summer Conferences, 1958 (Box 4)
    - IRE Conference, 1962 (Box 4)
    - Lecture Announcements, 1968-1970 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Electronics Conference, 1962 (Box 4)
    - Michigan Industry-University Research Conference, 1964 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Brochures, 1950-1956 (Box 4)
    - NASA Visit, 1968 (Box 4)
    - Power Systems Lab Dedication, 1964 (Box 4)
    - Radar Symposium, 1962 (Box 4)
    - Research Review, 1968 (Box 4)
    - Seminar in Honor of Dow, 1964 (Box 4)
    - Summer Courses, 1956-1957 (Box 4)
    - Summer Electronics Symposium, Personnel File, 1950 (Box 4)
    - URSI and IEEE G-AP Meeting, 1967 (Box 4)
    - URSI Symposium, 1956 (Box 4)
    - Voltage-Tunable Magnetrons Conference, 1956 (Box 4)
- Research, 1929-1964
  The Research series is composed of two subseries: Industrial Research and Government Research. The extent of documentation varies considerably among individual projects, but may include correspondence, reports, notes, photographs and experimental data, and budget information. Each subseries consists of separate files for the various sponsored projects involving Dow as a director or participant. The Industrial Research subseries begins with a general correspondence file; the remainder of the materials are arranged alphabetically by the name of the sponsoring company. Where a project number has been identified, it is included in the folder title. Among the more significant of these projects is Dow's work for the Fisher Body Division of General Motors on the use of high-frequency power for welding sheet metal (which resulted in several patents).
  The Government Research subseries begins with projects which could not be identified by a project number, listed alphabetically. The remainder of the folders in the subseries are organized by project number. The following materials are particularly significant: Project 669 which employed U-2 rockets in investigations of the ionosphere; Project 679, (or "Wizard") which involved development of guidance systems for an anti-ballistic missile, and Project M2144, (known as "Wolverine," and later "Project Michigan") which encompassed a wide range of military sponsored research.
  - Industrial Research, 1929-1966
    - Correspondence, 1941-1963 (Box 4)
    - AC Spark Plug-General Motors, 1960-1961 (Box 4)
    - American Car and Foundry Co. (Project Tinkertoy), 1953 (Box 4)
    - Bell Telephone Lab, 1939
      - Diary, Summer 1939 (Box 5)
      - Special Circuit Design, 1939 (Box 5)
      - Blueprints and Charts, 1939 (Box 5)
      - Contact Protection, 1939 (Box 5)
    - Binks Manufacturing Co., 1953 (Box 5)
    - Consumers Power Company, 1963-1966
      - Correspondence, 1963-1966 (Box 5)
      - Reports, 1965-1966 (Box 5)
    - Detroit-Edison Co. (Project 546), 1929-1930
      - Original Data, 1929 (Box 5)
      - Tabulation Sheets, 1929 (Box 5)
      - Computations from Data, 1929 (Box 5)
      - Reports, 1929 (Box 5)
      - Copies of paper sent to Physical Review, 1930 (Box 5)
    - Ethyl Gasoline Corp., 1938-1945 (Box 5)
    - Fisher Body (Project M330), 1938-1949
      - Correspondence, 1938-1949
        - 1938-1940 (Box 5)
        - 1941 (Box 5)
        - 1942 (Box 5)
        - 1943-1944 (Box 5)
        - 1945-1949 (Box 5)
      - Monthly Reports, April 1941-June 1942 (Box 5)
      - Monthly Reports, July 1942-May 1943 (Box 5)
      - Notes and Experimental Data, 1941-1943; 5 folders (Box 5)
      - Blueprints and Research Data, 1941-1943 (Box 6)
      - Microphotographs and photographs of machinery, 1941 (Box 6)
      - Final Report, 1944 (Box 6)
      - Supplement to Final Report, 1945 (Box 6)
      - Patents, 1941-1943 (Box 6)
      - Patents, 1944-1945 (Box 6)
    - Progressive Welder Co., 1941 (Box 6)
    - Schwarze Electric Company (Project M176), 1933 (Box 6)
    - Sciaky Welder Corp., 1940-1949
      - Correspondence, 1940-1949 (Box 6)
      - Data book, 1940 (Box 6)
      - Reports, 1940-1941 (Box 6)
  - Government Research, 1943-1964
    - National Bureau of Standards, 1945-1952
      - Correspondence
        - 1945 (Box 6)
        - 1946 (Box 6)
        - 1947 (Box 6)
        - 1948 (Box 6)
        - 1949-1951 (Box 6)
        - 1952 (Box 6)
      - Experimental Data and Notes (Box 6)
    - Radio Research Lab, Harvard University, 1943-1945 (Box 6)
    - Watson Laboratories, 1946 (Box 6)
    - Project M440 (Light Transient Oscilloscope), 1942-1945 (Box 6)
    - Project M669-A (use of V2 rockets to study the upper atmosphere), 1946-1948
      - Correspondence, 1947-1948 (Box 6)
      - Notes and Reports, 1946-1947; 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Photographs (Box 7)
    - Project M679 ("Wizard"), 1945-1951
      - Correspondence, 1945-1946 (Box 7)
      - Correspondence, 1947-1951 (Box 7)
      - Technical Reports, 1946-1948 (Box 7)
      - Weekly Reports, November-December 1949 (Box 7)
      - Technical Advisory Board Minutes, 1947-1949 (Box 7)
      - Budget Statements, 1946-1950 (Box 7)
    - Project M679Db (Missile Guidance), 1948-1949 (Box 7)
    - Project M689 (Loan of Equipment), 1947-1952 (Box 7)
    - Project M824, 1950 (Box 7)
    - Project M2048 (Arc Discharge Through a Liquid), 1953 (Box 7)
    - Project M2091 (Study of Armament Systems), 1952-1954
      - Correspondence, 1953-1954 (Box 7)
      - Original trip reports, 1952-1953 (Box 7)
      - Report, 1953 (Box 7)
      - Final Report, circa 1953 (Box 7)
    - Project M2096 (Physical Properties of the Upper Atmosphere), 1952-1957 (Box 7)
    - Project M2144 ("Project Michigan"), 1953-1957 (Box 7)
    - Project M2269 (Diamond Ordnance Fuze Laboratories), 1953-1964
      - Correspondence, 1953-1964 (Box 7)
      - Reports and Notes, 1955-1958 (Box 7)
    - Project M2275 (an electron tube project), 1955-1956 (Box 7)
    - Project M2485, 1956 (Box 7)
    - Project M2522, 1958 (Box 7)
    - Project M2836, 1959 (Box 7)
    - Project 05834 (Low Voltage Arc Studies), 1964 (Box 7)
- Professional Organizations, 1932-1977
  The Professional Organizations series represents Dow's extensive commitment to the advancement of science and the engineering profession through participation in national organizations. This series also contains Dow's files relating to his participation in the Rocket and Satellite Research Panel, the Upper Atmosphere Rocket Research Panel and the United States National Committee for the International Geophysical Year Technical Panel on Rocketry.
  - American Geophysical Union, 1962 (Box 8)
  - American Institute of Electrical Engineers (AIEE), 1941-1966
    - Committee on Computing Devices, 1951-1963
      - Correspondence, 1951-1963
        - 1951-1954 (Box 8)
        - 1955-1956 (Box 8)
        - 1957 (Box 8)
        - Correspondence (Box 8)
        - 1959 (Box 8)
        - 1960 (Box 8)
        - 1961, 2 folders (Box 8)
        - 1962 (Box 8)
        - 1963 (Box 8)
    - Committee on Electron Tubes, 1948-1964
      - 1948 (Box 8)
      - 1951-1955 (Box 8)
      - 1957-1964 (Box 8)
    - Committee on Electronics, 1942-1961
      - Correspondence, 1942-1961
        - 1942-1944 (Box 8)
        - 1945 (Box 8)
        - 1946 (Box 8)
        - 1947, 2 folders (Box 8)
        - 1948 (Box 9)
        - 1950-1953 (Box 9)
        - 1954 (Box 9)
        - 1955 (Box 9)
        - 1956-1961 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence and Organizational Charts, 1941-1961 (Box 9)
    - Fellow Nominations, 1960-1964 (Box 9)
    - Michigan Section, 1946-1963
      - Correspondence, 1959-1963 (Box 9)
      - Promotions and Transfers to Fellow Grade, 1946-1953
        - 1946-1953 (Box 9)
        - 1953-1956 (Box 9)
        - 1956-1958 (Box 9)
      - Operations Manual, 1959 (Box 9)
    - National Electronics Conference (NEC), 1949-1966
      - Correspondence, 1949-1966
        - 1949-1950 (Box 9)
        - 1949-1950 (Box 9)
        - 1953 (Box 9)
          (Includes additional notes)
        - 1954-1966 (Box 9)
    - New Activities Committee, 1960-1963
      - 1960-1961 (Box 9)
      - 1962-1963 (Box 9)
    - Prize Awards Committee, 1951 (Box 9)
    - Research Committee, 1954-1963
      - 1954, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - 1955 (Box 9)
      - 1956 (Box 10)
      - 1957 (Box 10)
      - 1958 (Box 10)
      - 1959 (Box 10)
      - 1960 (Box 10)
      - 1961-1963 (Box 10)
    - Science and Electronics Division Committee, 1952-1963
      - 1952-1954 (Box 10)
      - 1955-1956 (Box 10)
      - 1957-1960 (Box 10)
      - 1961-1963 (Box 10)
      - Summer Convention, Mexico City, 1948 (Box 10)
  - American Physical Society, 1949-1964 (Box 10)
  - American Society for Engineering Education (ASEE), 1940-1965
    - 1940-1947 (Box 10)
    - 1960-1965 (Box 10)
    - Michigan Section Meetings, 1964 (Box 10)
    - Solid State Electronics Workshop (ASEE/IRE) at Purdue, 1960 (Box 10)
  - American Welding Society, 1938-1941 (Box 10)
  - Institute of Electrical & Electronic Engineers (IEEE), 1959-1977